Finding Aid for the Vandy Goes to War: World War II Remembered Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Vandy Goes to War: World War II Remembered Collection
2008
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0634
1.25 linear feet
Scope and Content and History Note
Vandy Goes to War: World War II Remembered an Oral History was begun in the autumn of 2006 with the intention of making a record of the various experiences of Vanderbilt and Peabody men and women during the World War II. The electronic archive, to be read and listened to is available at this link:
Paper copies of the transcripts and other supporting materials donated by the participants are housed in Special Collections and University Archives. Altogether there are forty participants. The interviews are complemented by a number of digitized photographs from the personal collections of some of the contributors and include ninety pages from a World War II photograph journal of a Naval officer’s tour of duty in the South Pacific.
This project records the histories and reminiscences of men and women who attended or had connections with Vanderbilt and Peabody during the war years and documents their experiences in the service and on the campus during that time and afterward when some came back to school and attended on the G.I. Bill. The interviews include eye witness accounts of soldiers fighting at the Battle of the Bulge in the winter of 1944 and early 1945, in the Far East at Okinawa, flying aerial reconnaissance in the European theatre, and medical and hospital work in North Africa and southern Italy. One soldier, a prisoner of war in a camp in Germany tells his story. Another tells of being an eighteen year old soldier liberating prisoners from Dachau Concentration camp in southern Germany. Women speak of taking leadership positions in campus life, when so many men had gone to war and of their efforts on the home front and of the realities of rationing and limited necessities.
This project was begun in the fall of 2006; the final interviews were completed in the last part of 2007.
Juanita Murray, Director of Special Collections and University Archives and Kathy Smith, Associate University Archivist are the co-ordinators for the project. Molly Dohrmann conducted all of the interviews for this oral history.
- Transciptions of the interviews with dates and timings and biographical data sheets
  - Anderson, Lyttleton C., Jr., January 4, 2007; 24:52 minutes (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bates, Douglas T., III, April 26, 2007; 19:10 minutes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bowers, Eugene, October 12, 2006; 15:13 minutes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bowman, Dunklin C., December 1, 2006; 23:58 minutes (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Branscomb, Ben and Jane, September 29, 2006; 55:30 minutes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bugel, Alice H., June 1, 2007; 48:56 minutes (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Durham, Walter T., September 26, 2006; 50:48 minutes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eskind, Allen S., September 28, 2006; 1:00:15 minutes (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - George, Ted M., January 23, 2007; 13:39 minutes (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Healy, Robert, August 16, 2007; 16:24 minutes (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Holcomb, George W., Jr. Biographical data form only (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Holladay, Virginia June 27, 2007; pt. 1- 6:20; pt. 2- 2:03 minutes (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Holroyd, Sara, October 18, 2006; 9:53 minutes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - James, David, Jr., January 23, 2007; 20:42 minutes (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jenkins, Lillian Bloodworth, December 13, 2006; 6:21 minutes (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Jones, Wayman Morris, December 12, 2006; 11:52 minutes (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Larsen, James and Anne, October 18, 2006; 1:18:25 minutes (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Norman, Haywood Petrie, III, January 19, 2007; 10:18 minutes (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Owen, Tom and Mary (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Owen, Susan, December 26, 2006; 18:20 minutes (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Payne, Maxwell Carr, Jr., November 20, 2006; 21:35 minutes (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pearsall, Sam, October 10, 2007; pt. 1, 56:03; pt. 2, 2:00; pt. 3, 1:15; pt. 4, 5:12 minutes (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Smith, Marion L., December 5, 2006; 5:22 minutes (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Stewart, John M., October 11, 2006; 15:34 minutes (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Still, Elizabeth Blair, December 14, 2006; 8:42 minutes (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tacker, Frank, January 18, 2007; 45:42 minutes (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Thomas, George D., Jr., January 11, 2007; 24:44 minutes (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Thompson, Joe and Martha, December 1, 2006; pt. 1, 49:59, pt. 2, 4:40 minutes (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Tuck, James, February 21, 2007; 5:32 minutes (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Webb, James C., Jr., August 1, 2007; 29:17 minutes (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Williams, Benjamin B., October 18, 2007; 1:05:10 minutes (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Williams, Jack, January 9, 2007; 22:52 minutes (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Worrell, Estelle Ansley, December 5, 2006; 29:33 minutes (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Wright, Harold L., February 14, 2007; pt. 1, 5:40; pt. 2, :00:41 minutes (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Wright, Jean A., February 20, 2007; 29:05 minutes (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Related materials and photographs
  - Anderson, Lyttleton Photocopies of maps and other items of general interest (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Lyttleton Contact sheets of scanned photographs sc.mss.0634.007 - .035;Battle of the Bulge, Dec. 16, 1944 - Jan.25, 1945, personal collection with identification (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brammer, Harry M., Jr World War II History Book with introductory letter by Harry M. Brammer, III, M.D. The First Platoon of the 44th Cavalry Reconnaissance Troop, 44th Infantry Division Form TX Copyrighted U.S. Patent Office - TXU 352 580, 21 December 1988 by Harry Murray Brammer, Jr. (P.F.C. - U.S. Army) Serial No. 35091120 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Branscomb, Ben and Jane “Ben Branscomb Reviews 60 Years of Discovery” in UABSYNOPSIS, Vol. 25, No. 18, August 14, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bugel, Alice H. Transcript of oral history interview on September 13, 2002, 22 pages; photocopy of an article on the 8th Evacuation Hospital, University of Virginia with photos of Alice Bugel and her notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bugel, Alice H. Humor In Uniform; Memories of My Mother: A Remembrance of Johanna E. Moline by Anna Lisa Moline; Reminiscences: My Life and Nursing Career by Anna Lisa Moline; “She Was There: A W.W.II War Veterans Story” in The Veteran Tribune, June 2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bugel, Alice H. Contact sheets of scanned photographs sc.mss.0634. 038 - .072, personal collection of World War II photos taken in the U. S., North Africa, and Italy with identifications (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Eskind, Allen S. Finding aid for the Allen S. Eskind World War II Papers (MSS 633) which includes the link to the 90 page photograph album of digitized images from his tour of duty in the South Pacific during the war. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - George, Ted M. A Life in the Twentieth Century - an autobiography with chapters on his World War II service and his time at Vanderbilt (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Holladay, Virginia M. Written reminiscences of her time at Vanderbilt during the years 1942-1946. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Holroyd, Sara Finding aid for the Sara Holroyd World War II and George Peabody for Teachers Collection (MSS 654) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - James, David H. 2 articles “A Mission in Memphis” Spring 1988, p. 40; “A Selfless Career” Fall 2002, in Vanderbilt Medicine (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Larsen, James Contact sheets of scans mss images 0634.036 - .037 of James Larsen in uniform on the Vanderbilt Campus (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Owen, Thomas B World War II materials - award of Bronze Star and Purple Heart; Lists of soldiers wounded in action and killed in action, Third Battalion; “On the Point of the Spear: Some Experiences of a Marine Rifleman During the Battle for the Island of Okinawa in April, May, and June of 1945” by James S. White, G Company, 3rd Battalion, 29th Marines, Sixth Marine Division (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Owen, Thomas B. and Mary P., Owen, Susan Photocopies of personal and biographical materials, including “A Tribute to Coach Tommy Owen.” (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Owen, Thomas B. and Mary P. Owen, Susan Photocopies of personal and biographical materials and newspaper articles relating to his athletic and sports career at Vanderbilt University and with newspaper articles on Mary P.Owen. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pearsall, Sam Photocopy of a World War II Notebook - “World War II as Fought and Won by Sam Pearsall II” (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pearsall, Sam Photocopies of a transcript of a ship’s bridge signal log of February 1944; Chapter III of Oheka Castle - the Kahn mansion; remarks made by Sam Pearsall at a banquet; the Merchant Seamen Memorial Fund; and newspaper articles (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Stewart, John M. Brief Autobiography for the Vanderbilt Reunion of the class of, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Tacker, James Frank, Jr “WWII Battle of the Bulge Progresses: Frank Tacker Taken Prisoner of War” December 1994; photocopy of a map of WWII Prison camps in Europe (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Tacker, James Frank, Jr. “Bulge Bugle” official publication of Veterans of the Battle of the Bulge, February 2006, November 2006; “The Cub of the Golden Lion” veterans of the 106th Infantry Division, July-August-September 2005, October-November-December 2006 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Thompson, Joe and Martha Photocopy of press release for his book Tiger Joe: a Photographic Diary of a World War II Aerial Reconnaissance Pilot, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Williams, Benjamin B. Photocopies of autobiography “Ben Williams in War and Peace”; “Bridge on the River Rhine” in the History Channel Magazine, June 2006; letter with memories of Vanderbilt professors (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Worrell, Estelle A. Photocopy of newspaper clipping, Peabody Dames (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Worrell, Estelle A. and Norman Contact sheets of scanned photographs sc.mss.0634.001 - .006, the Peabody campus in the snow; Veterans Village at Peabody, c., 1951 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - “Were You Here During World War II” in Vanderbilt Magazine, Summer, “Vandy Goes to War: An Oral History Project” by Lew Harris in Acorn Chronicle, Summer; 2006; 2007 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - General Patton’s Prayer during the Battle of the Bulge (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Web information on the Battle of the Bulge (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Individual contact and correspondence information, and other administrative materials.
  - Anderson, Lyttleton (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bates, Douglas T., III (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bowers, Eugene (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bowman, Dunklin, Jr. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Brammer, Harry M., III (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Branscomb, Ben and Jane (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bugel, Alice H. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Durham, Walter T. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Eskind, Allen S. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - George, Ted M. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Healy, Robert (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Holcomb, George, Jr. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Holladay, Virginia (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Holroyd, Sara (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - James, David H. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Jenkins, Lillian Bloodworth (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jones, Wayman Morris (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Larsen, James and Anne (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Norman, Heywood Petrie, III (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Owen, Thomas B. and Mary Susan Owen (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Payne, M. Carr, Jr. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Pearsall, Samuet H., Jr. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Smith, Marion L. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Stewart, John M. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Blair-Still, Elizabeth (Betty Carlisle) (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Tacker, James Frank, Jr. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Thomas, George D., Jr. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Thompson, Joe and Martha (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Tuck, James (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Webb, James A., Jr. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Williams, Benjamin B. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Williams, Jack (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Worrell, Estelle (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Wright, Harold L. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Wright, Jean A. (Box 3, Folder 35)
- People who did not participate but were contacted for this oral history project:
  - Anderson, John N. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Browning, Earl (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Burkett, B. G. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Collins, Willard (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Cowden, Miriam (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Gowen, Jesse L., Jr. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Jolly, Jean Hagy (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Kittrell, Oliver (Kit) and Carolyn (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Legler, Frank C. (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Noel, Andromedia (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Schultz, Lloyd E. (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Spiegel, George (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Stockell, Charles W. (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Townes, Emily Manchester (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Wells, William W. (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Signed Project Release Forms – kept in Director’s office (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Deed of Gift form signed by Alice H. Bugel (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence with Lew Harris, editor of the Acorn Chronicle for article (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Index of interviewees Index of names and places for transcription service (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - General notes and correspondence on the project (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Biographical data forms - blank (Box 3, Folder 56)
- 1 – 33.
  - Original transcripts with corrections